[
    {
    "question": "Identify cyber security threat not a type of malware.",
    "answer": "Phishing",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "5 The internet and its uses",
    "tags": [
      "multiple-choice"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "malware",
      "phishing",
      "not malware"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify another example of malware.",
    "answer": "Any one from:\n• Spyware // Keylogger\n• Adware\n• Trojan horse",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "5 The internet and its uses",
    "tags": [
      "identify"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "malware",
      "example",
      "trojan"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify software used to find and remove malware.",
    "answer": "Anti-malware",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "4 Software",
    "tags": [
      "identify"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "malware removal",
      "anti-virus",
      "software"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Convert binary 11100011 to denary.",
    "answer": "227",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "conversion"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "binary to denary",
      "conversion"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Convert binary 11100011 to hexadecimal.",
    "answer": "One mark for each correct character in the correct order:\nE3",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "conversion"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "binary to hexadecimal",
      "conversion"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Perform logical left shift of 2 places on binary 11100011.",
    "answer": "1\n0 0 0 1 1 0 0 0",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "logical shift"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "logical left shift",
      "binary shift"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Give two's complement for denary -99.",
    "answer": "One mark for suitable working method e.g. flip and add 1\nOne mark for correct answer\n• 10011101",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "two's complement"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "two's complement",
      "-99",
      "negative binary"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Add binary numbers 01001100 and 11100011.",
    "answer": "One mark for each correct nibble (max 2)\nOne mark for correct working e.g. correct carries\nOne mark for showing overflow bit\n 1\n 1 1 1 0 0 0 1 1\n+ 0 1 0 0 1 1 0 0\n1 0 0 1 0 1 1 1 1",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "binary addition"
    ],
    "marks": 4,
    "keywords": [
      "binary addition",
      "8-bit"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Define clock speed.",
    "answer": "The maximum number of FDE cycles/instructions a CPU can perform/process/execute in a second",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "define"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "clock speed",
      "definition",
      "FDE cycles"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain effect of changing CPU from 2 GHz to 3 GHz.",
    "answer": "Increases/improves the performance // Tasks can be performed quicker/faster\n… because more FDE cycles/instructions can be processed in a second",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "explain"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "CPU",
      "clock speed",
      "performance",
      "2GHz to 3GHz"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe MAR role in FDE cycle.",
    "answer": "Stores addresses …\n… of next instruction/data to be fetched // where data is to be written to",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "describe"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "MAR",
      "role",
      "FDE cycle",
      "address storage"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "State name of list of machine code commands CPU can process.",
    "answer": "Instruction set",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "state"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "machine code",
      "instruction set",
      "CPU commands"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Give two characteristics of embedded system.",
    "answer": "Any two from:\n• Performs a single/limited/dedicated function/task\n• It has a microprocessor\n• It has dedicated hardware\n• Uses firmware\n• It is normally built into a larger device/system\n• User normally cannot reprogram\n• It does not require much power\n• It is cheap to manufacture\n• Works automatically // works without human intervention\n• It is small (in size)\n• It is a real-time system",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "give"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "embedded system",
      "characteristics",
      "dedicated",
      "limited resources"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Circle three other examples of embedded system.",
    "answer": "One mark for each correct system:\n• security light system\n• freezer\n• vending machine",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "circle"
    ],
    "marks": 3,
    "keywords": [
      "embedded system",
      "examples",
      "freezer",
      "security light",
      "vending machine"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Give one benefit of higher sample rate for sound recording.",
    "answer": "Any one from:\n• The recording of the song is more accurate/closer to original",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "give"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "sample rate",
      "benefit",
      "sound quality"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Give one drawback of higher sample rate.",
    "answer": "Any one from:\n• The file size will be increased\n• The file will require more storage space",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "give"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "sample rate",
      "drawback",
      "file size"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Define sample resolution.",
    "answer": "Any two from:\n• The number of bits that are used per sample\n• … that provides the variation in amplitude that can be stored for each sample // defines the number of different amplitudes that can be recorded\n• … that determines how quiet/loud the sounds are that can be recorded\n• Example e.g. 16-bit",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "define"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "sample resolution",
      "definition",
      "bits per sample"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify compression method that doesn't permanently remove data.",
    "answer": "Lossless",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "1 Data representation",
    "tags": [
      "identify"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "compression",
      "lossless",
      "no data removal"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Complete table about data transmission methods.",
    "answer": "One mark for each correct data transmission method:\ndata transmission method\nserial simplex\nparallel half-duplex\nserial full-duplex\nparallel simplex",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "2 Data transmission",
    "tags": [
      "complete"
    ],
    "marks": 4,
    "keywords": [
      "data transmission",
      "serial",
      "parallel",
      "simplex",
      "half-duplex",
      "full-duplex"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify two input devices for automatic ticket reading.",
    "answer": "Any two from e.g.\n• Barcode scanner\n• QR code scanner\n• Digital camera",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "identify"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "input devices",
      "ticket reading",
      "barcode",
      "RFID"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain how sensor and microprocessor check train door closure.",
    "answer": "Any six from:\n• Proximity/infrared/pressure sensor used\n• Sensor continually sends digitised data to microprocessor // When driver pushes button, sensor sends digitised data to the microprocessor\n• Microprocessor compares data to stored value(s)\n• If in range/out of range/matches, microprocessor sends signal to close the door\n• Actuator used to close door\n• If not in range/out of range/does not match door will not close // If not in range/out of range/does not match actuator not activated/signal not sent as passenger in door // If not in range/out of range/does not match a timer is set to check again // If not in range/out of range/does not match a signal is sent to alert the driver/output a message\n• This process repeats until the door can close",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "explain"
    ],
    "marks": 6,
    "keywords": [
      "sensor",
      "microprocessor",
      "train door",
      "safety",
      "passenger detection"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify security solution against data interception.",
    "answer": "Encryption …\n… if the data is intercepted it will be meaningless (because they do not have the decryption key)",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "5 The internet and its uses",
    "tags": [
      "identify"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "data interception",
      "security solution",
      "encryption"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Complete table about internet terms.",
    "answer": "Term\nworld wide web\ncookie\nuniform resource locator (URL)\nweb server\nhypertext markup language // HTML\nhypertext transfer protocol // HTTP",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "5 The internet and its uses",
    "tags": [
      "complete"
    ],
    "marks": 6,
    "keywords": [
      "internet terms",
      "WWW",
      "cookie",
      "URL",
      "web server",
      "HTML",
      "HTTP"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "State one main characteristic of AI system.",
    "answer": "Any one from:\n• The ability to learn/adapt // machine learning abilities\n• The collection of data and the rules for using that data\n• The ability to reason // has problem solving abilities // makes predictions\n• Simulates intelligent/human behaviour\n• Analyses patterns",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "state"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "AI",
      "characteristic",
      "learning"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain how expert system operates.",
    "answer": "Any six from:\n• It has an interface …\n• … used to input data/view output\n• It has a knowledge base\n• It has a rule base\n• It has an inference engine\n• Applies the rule base to/and the knowledge base to provide output/diagnosis/result/solution/decision\n• Decides what to ask next based on the data input",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "explain"
    ],
    "marks": 4,
    "keywords": [
      "expert system",
      "operation",
      "knowledge base",
      "inference engine"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify what flow sensor measures.",
    "answer": "Amount of liquid/gas/steam flowing/moving through an environment",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "identify"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "flow sensor",
      "measures",
      "flow rate"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain one advantage of automated system for employees.",
    "answer": "Two from (for benefit and matching description) e.g.:\n• Increases safety\n• …meaning that workers do not need to go into dangerous areas to collect data/make checks/do dangerous tasks\n• Can increase jobs/skills\n• …as employees are needed to learn/maintain the equipment\n• No need to do repetitive tasks\n• … so, they can use their time on other/more skilled tasks",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "explain"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "automated system",
      "advantage",
      "employees",
      "safety"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain one disadvantage of automated system for owners.",
    "answer": "Two from (for drawback and matching description) e.g.:\n• High set-up/installation costs\n• … it would mean the company need to find a lot of money up front to pay for the equipment // employees will need training\n• Utility/maintenance/repair costs\n• … increase in bills such as electricity // skilled employees will be required to maintain the system // equipment will break/need updating\n• Deskilling of the workforce\n• … may mean that workers will no longer have the skills for some of the manufacturing jobs, should the equipment break",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "explain"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "automated system",
      "disadvantage",
      "owners",
      "cost"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Give two other features of digital currency.",
    "answer": "Any two from:\n• Only exists electronically\n• Can be a decentralised system\n• Can be a centralised system\n• Usually encrypted",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "give"
    ],
    "marks": 2,
    "keywords": [
      "digital currency",
      "features",
      "decentralized",
      "cryptography"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify process using digital ledger to track digital currency.",
    "answer": "Blockchain",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "6 Automated and emerging technologies",
    "tags": [
      "identify"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "digital ledger",
      "blockchain",
      "digital currency"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify example of primary storage.",
    "answer": "Random access memory (RAM)",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "multiple-choice"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "primary storage",
      "example",
      "RAM"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Give one characteristic of primary storage.",
    "answer": "Any one from:\n• Directly accessed by the CPU\n• Has both volatile and non-volatile storage",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "give"
    ],
    "marks": 1,
    "keywords": [
      "primary storage",
      "characteristic",
      "volatile"
    ]
  },
  {
    "question": "Complete description about virtual memory.",
    "answer": "One mark for each correct term in the correct order:\n• Random access memory (RAM)\n• Hard disk drive (HDD)\n• Pages\n• Random access memory (RAM)\n• Virtual memory // Hard disk drive (HDD)",
    "paper": "W24P12",
    "topic": "3 Hardware",
    "tags": [
      "complete"
    ],
    "marks": 5,
    "keywords": [
      "virtual memory",
      "RAM",
      "HDD",
      "pages"
    ]
  }
]